翻译人员: Geoff Chen
校对人员: Zhiting Chen
我这辈子都是个旅行者。I'm a lifelong traveler.
即使还是一个小孩子的时候，Even as a little kid,
我便了解，事实上，I was actually working out
that it would be cheaper
去读英国寄宿学校会比to go to boarding school in England
去加州父母家附近
最好的学校就读还来得便宜。than just to the best school down the road
from my parents' house in California.
所以，当我 9 岁时，So, from the time I was nine years old
我在一年中，会独自飞行几回，I was flying alone several times a year
穿越北极，就只是去上学。over the North Pole, just to go to school.
当然，飞得越频繁，
我越是爱上旅行，And of course the more I flew
the more I came to love to fly,
所以就在我高中毕业后一周，so the very week after I graduated
from high school,
我找到一份清理桌子的工作，I got a job mopping tables
为了让自己可以在 18 岁那年，so that I could spend
every season of my 18th year
在地球不同的大陆上，
分别待上一季。on a different continent.
接着，几乎不可避免地
我成了一个旅游作家，And then, almost inevitably,
I became a travel writer
使我的工作和志趣
可以结合在一块儿。so my job and my joy could become one.
我真的开始发觉
如果你可以幸运地And I really began to feel
that if you were lucky enough
漫步于西藏的烛光寺庙，to walk around
the candlelit temples of Tibet
或者在音乐的缭绕间or to wander along the seafronts in Havana
悠然信步于哈瓦那海岸，with music passing all around you,
你便能将那声音、天际you could bring those sounds
and the high cobalt skies
与靛蓝海洋的闪烁光芒and the flash of the blue ocean
带给你家乡的朋友，back to your friends at home,
真确地捎来些许神奇，and really bring some magic
点亮自身生命。and clarity to your own life.
除了，如你们所知，Except, as you all know,
当旅行时，你学到的第一件事情是one of the first things you learn
when you travel
你必须以正确的视角看世界，
否则大地依然黯淡无光。is that nowhere is magical
unless you can bring the right eyes to it.
你带一个易怒的男人爬喜马拉雅山，You take an angry man to the Himalayas,
他只会抱怨那儿的食物。he just starts complaining about the food.
我发现，有点怪异的是，And I found that the best way
最好的让自己可以培养that I could develop more attentive
and more appreciative eyes
更专注和更珍惜世界的视角的诀窍是was, oddly,
哪儿都不去，静止于原处即可。by going nowhere, just by sitting still.
当然呆在原地正是我们许多人
寻常所得到的东西，And of course sitting still
is how many of us get
我们都渴望在快速的生活中获得休息。what we most crave and need
in our accelerated lives, a break.
但那却是我唯一的方法，But it was also the only way
让自己可以重历自身的经验幻灯，that I could find to sift through
the slideshow of my experience
理解未来与过去。and make sense of the future and the past.
如此，我惊异地发现，And so, to my great surprise,
我发现无所去处I found that going nowhere
和游览西藏或古巴一样，令人兴奋。was at least as exciting
as going to Tibet or to Cuba.
无所去处，只不过意谓着And by going nowhere,
I mean nothing more intimidating
每天花几分钟，than taking a few minutes out of every day
或每季花几天，or a few days out of every season,
甚至，如同有些人所做的，or even, as some people do,
在生命中花上几年a few years out of a life
长久地静思于某处，in order to sit still long enough
寻找感动你最多的一瞬，to find out what moves you most,
回忆你最真实的幸福时刻，to recall where your truest happiness lies
同时记住，and to remember that sometimes
有时候，谋生与生活making a living and making a life
彼此是处于光谱线上的两端的。point in opposite directions.
当然，这是明智的众生历经几百年And of course, this is what wise beings
through the centuries
从每个传统中所告诉我们的。from every tradition have been telling us.
这是一个古老的概念。It's an old idea.
早在两千多年前，
斯多葛学派提醒我们More than 2,000 years ago,
the Stoics were reminding us
并不是我们的经验
成就了我们的生命，it's not our experience
that makes our lives,
而是我们用那经验做了什么。it's what we do with it.
想象一下，一阵飓风
迅速扑向你的城市，Imagine a hurricane suddenly
sweeps through your town
将所有一切化为废墟。and reduces every last thing to rubble.
某个人身心遭受终身顿挫，One man is traumatized for life.
但另一个人，也许甚至是他的兄弟，
却几乎感觉释怀，But another, maybe even his brother,
almost feels liberated,
并认定，这是一个可以
使自己重获新生的重要机会。and decides this is a great chance
to start his life anew.
这是同样的事件，It's exactly the same event,
截然不同的回应。but radically different responses.
没有什么是绝对的好坏， 正如莎士比亚
在《哈姆雷特》中所告诉我们的，There is nothing either good or bad,
as Shakespeare told us in "Hamlet,"
好坏由思维决定。but thinking makes it so.
这无疑就是我
作为一个旅者的经验。And this has certainly been
my experience as a traveler.
24 年前，我完成了一次
最不可思议的旅程：Twenty-four years ago I took
the most mind-bending trip
橫跨朝鮮。across North Korea.
但这次旅行只持续了几天。But the trip lasted a few days.
这经验对于无所去处的我来说，
允许我可以在心思中回朔，What I've done with it sitting still,
going back to it in my head,
试着了解它，让它在我的思维中
寻得一个位置，trying to understand it,
finding a place for it in my thinking,
在那儿，它已存留了 24 年，that's lasted 24 years already
而且很可能会在我这生中，
一直持续下去。and will probably last a lifetime.
换句话说， 这次旅行，
带给我一些惊人的景致，The trip, in other words,
gave me some amazing sights,
但唯有处于静止的状态but it's only sitting still
才让我得以将这些风景线
化为更长的见识。that allows me to turn those
into lasting insights.
我有时会想，我们的生活And I sometimes think
that so much of our life
有太多东西发生在
我们自己的脑袋里，takes place inside our heads,
在回忆中，在想象里，
透过诠释，或是猜测，in memory or imagination
or interpretation or speculation,
如果我真想改变我的生命，that if I really want to change my life
我可能最好从
改变我的思维开始。I might best begin by changing my mind.
同样，这一切都不是新想法；Again, none of this is new;
这就是为什么莎士比亚和斯多葛学派
在几个世纪前就告诉我们，that's why Shakespeare and the Stoics
were telling us this centuries ago,
然而，莎士比亚从未面对过
一天收到两百多封电邮的日子。but Shakespeare never had to face
200 emails in a day.
（笑声）(Laughter)
据我所知，斯多葛派的学者们
也没待在脸书上。The Stoics, as far as I know,
were not on Facebook.
我们都知道，在我们的按需生活中，We all know that in our on-demand lives,
一种最迫切需要之物one of the things that's most on demand
就是自己。is ourselves.
无论我们处于何处，处于何时，
无论是夜晚或白天中的任何时刻，Wherever we are, any time of night or day,
我们的老板，垃圾邮件，
我们的父母都能找到我们。our bosses, junk-mailers,
our parents can get to us.
社会学家近年来所发现的是，Sociologists have actually found
that in recent years
当今美国人的工作时间
竟然比 50 年前还少，Americans are working fewer hours
than 50 years ago,
但我们却觉得自己的工时更长。but we feel as if we're working more.
我们有越来越多的
可以用来节省时间的设备，We have more and more time-saving devices,
但有时，时间似乎越来越少。but sometimes, it seems,
less and less time.
我们比以前更容易与We can more and more easily
make contact with people
身处地球另一端的人们联系，on the furthest corners of the planet,
但有时候，在那过程中，but sometimes in that process
我们与自己断了线。we lose contact with ourselves.
作为一个旅行者，
让我最为诧异的事情之一就是And one of my biggest surprises
as a traveler
我发现，时常，往往那些has been to find
that often it's exactly the people
最使我们能够走向世界各地的人who have most enabled us to get anywhere
却最希望身居原处。who are intent on going nowhere.
换句话说，正是那些In other words, precisely those beings
创造了打破旧时的who have created the technologies
限制人出游的科技的人们that override so many
of the limits of old,
才是最具智慧的个体，
他们理解限制的必须，are the ones wisest
about the need for limits,
甚至在面对科技本身时，亦是如此。even when it comes to technology.
有一次我造访谷歌总部，I once went to the Google headquarters
我见到了所有你们听说过的事；and I saw all the things
many of you have heard about;
室内树屋，蹦床，the indoor tree houses, the trampolines,
拥有 20% 属于自己付费工时的员工，workers at that time enjoying 20 percent
of their paid time free
允许他们的想象自由漫游。so that they could just let
their imaginations go wandering.
但更让我感到印象深刻的是，But what impressed me even more
当我正在等待我的数字身份证时，was that as I was waiting
for my digital I.D.,
有位谷歌员工告诉我一个项目，one Googler was telling me
about the program
说他正打算教许许多多的谷歌员工that he was about to start
to teach the many, many Googlers
来练习瑜伽，并成为训练师，who practice yoga
to become trainers in it,
而另外一个谷歌员工
向我阐述了一本他正想写的书，and the other Googler was telling me
about the book that he was about to write
一本关于内在寻索的书，on the inner search engine,
以及科学如何经验性地证明and the ways in which science
has empirically shown
打坐，或冥想that sitting still, or meditation,
不仅能促进健康，明晰思维，can lead not just to better
health or to clearer thinking,
甚至也能增加情绪智慧。but even to emotional intelligence.
我有另一个在硅谷工作的朋友，I have another friend in Silicon Valley
他的确是当前最前沿科技的who is really one
of the most eloquent spokesmen
最有说服力的代言人，事实上，for the latest technologies,
他是《连线》杂志的
创始人之一，凯文·凯利。and in fact was one of the founders
of Wired magazine, Kevin Kelly.
凯文当时正在写一本有关最新技术的书，And Kevin wrote his last book
on fresh technologies
但他家里却没有智能手机，
笔记本电脑，或者电视。without a smartphone
or a laptop or a TV in his home.
如同许多住在硅谷的人们，And like many in Silicon Valley,
他非常努力地观察he tries really hard to observe
那个称为互联网安息日的东西，what they call an Internet sabbath,
在每个星期，有 24 或 48 小时，whereby for 24 or 48 hours every week
他们会彻底地下线，they go completely offline
以寻求一点方向感，in order to gather the sense of direction
用来重新调整，并汲取
他们重新上线时之所需。and proportion they'll need
when they go online again.
有件科技可能尚未给予我们的是The one thing perhaps
that technology hasn't always given us
如何可以更聪明地使用科技。is a sense of how to make
the wisest use of technology.
谈到休息日，And when you speak of the sabbath,
让我们看看十戒吧，look at the Ten Commandments --
其中只有一个字的形容词涉及“神圣”，there's only one word there
for which the adjective "holy" is used,
而那就是安息日。and that's the Sabbath.
我拿起犹太圣典《托拉》，I pick up the Jewish holy book
of the Torah --
它最长的章节，就是关于安息日。its longest chapter, it's on the Sabbath.
我们都知道，这真是
我们所拥有的最大奢侈之一：And we all know that it's really
one of our greatest luxuries,
空。the empty space.
在许多音乐作品中，停顿或静默In many a piece of music,
it's the pause or the rest
赋予了这作品美丽形貌。that gives the piece
its beauty and its shape.
我知道，作为一个作家，And I know I as a writer
我时常会在页面中留下空白，will often try to include
a lot of empty space on the page
让读者可以完整地
领会我的思维与句法，so that the reader can complete
my thoughts and sentences
以留给想象呼吸的空间。and so that her imagination
has room to breathe.
现在，在实际的领域中，
当然有很多人，Now, in the physical domain,
of course, many people,
倘若他们稍微富余的话，if they have the resources,
会试着在国内拥有第二个家。will try to get a place in the country,
a second home.
我从未有过那些资源，I've never begun to have those resources,
但我有时记得
任何时候，若我想的话，but I sometimes remember
that any time I want,
我可以给自己放一天假，I can get a second home in time,
if not in space,
来适时地，获得第二个家。just by taking a day off.
当然，这从来就不容易，
每次我这么做，And it's never easy because, of course,
whenever I do I spend much of it
对于所有多出来的worried about all the extra stuff
会压垮我隔日工作天的忧虑就会出现。that's going to crash down on me
the following day.
有时我会觉得，我宁愿
放弃吃肉，性生活，或红酒，I sometimes think I'd rather give up
meat or sex or wine
也不愿失去任何一丁点查邮箱的机会。than the chance to check on my emails.
（笑声）(Laughter)
每一季，我的确给自己三天假期，And every season I do try to take
three days off on retreat
但关于丢下我妻子
以及忽略那些but a part of me still feels guilty
to be leaving my poor wife behind
老板寄来的看似紧急的邮件，and to be ignoring
all those seemingly urgent emails
以及错过一个朋友的派对，from my bosses
我内心某处仍然觉得有负罪感。and maybe to be missing
a friend's birthday party.
但一旦来到某个真正安静的地方，But as soon as I get
to a place of real quiet,
我才了解，只有去那儿，I realize that it's only by going there
我才能拥有全新的，
有创意的，或快意之事that I'll have anything fresh
or creative or joyful to share
和我妻子，上司和朋友分享。with my wife or bosses or friends.
否则，老天，Otherwise, really,
我能够加诸于他们的
仅仅是我的疲惫或分神状态，I'm just foisting on them
my exhaustion or my distractedness,
实在无福可言。which is no blessing at all.
所以当我 29 岁时，And so when I was 29,
我决定要重整自己全部的生活，I decided to remake my entire life
为了获得那无所去处的体验。in the light of going nowhere.
有天晚上，我从办公室回家，One evening I was coming back
from the office,
当时午夜时分，我正在出租车上，
经过了时代广场，it was after midnight, I was in a taxi
driving through Times Square,
我突然惊觉，自己仓皇度日and I suddenly realized
that I was racing around so much
以至于永远无法赶上自己的生活。I could never catch up with my life.
而我当时的生活，事实上And my life then, as it happened,
已差不多就和我小时梦想的一般。was pretty much the one
I might have dreamed of as a little boy.
我有非常有趣的朋友和同事，I had really interesting friends
and colleagues,
我在公园大道和第 20 街交口
有个非常棒的公寓。I had a nice apartment
on Park Avenue and 20th Street.
我有个对我来说绝佳的工作，
这工作让我得以撰写世界事务，I had, to me, a fascinating job
writing about world affairs,
但我从来未能将自己和它清楚分开，but I could never separate myself
enough from them
让自己倾听自己的思绪，to hear myself think --
或，去理解是否我真的处于喜乐之中。or really, to understand
if I was truly happy.
因此，我放弃我梦想中的工作，And so, I abandoned my dream life
就为了待在一个位于日本京都
某后街里的单间房内，for a single room on the backstreets
of Kyoto, Japan,
这地方长久以来产生了一种强烈的which was the place
that had long exerted a strong,
对我来说极为神秘的吸引力。really mysterious gravitational pull on me.
甚至在我孩提时代，Even as a child
我会看着一幅京都的画作
并感觉，我认出它来了，I would just look at a painting
of Kyoto and feel I recognized it;
在定睛审视它之前，我便知如此。I knew it before I ever laid eyes on it.
但它也是，如同大家所知，But it's also, as you all know,
是一个群山环绕的美丽城市，a beautiful city encircled by hills,
充满了 2000 多座寺庙和神社，filled with more than 2,000 temples
and shrines,
人们在那儿静默了 800 年以上之久。where people have been sitting still
for 800 years or more.
就在我搬到那儿不久，And quite soon after I moved there,
I ended up where I still am
我与现在的妻儿，with my wife, formerly our kids,
挤在一个有两间房的公寓里，
在一个不毛之地，in a two-room apartment
in the middle of nowhere
我们没有自行车，没有车，where we have no bicycle, no car,
没有可以理解的电视节目，no TV I can understand,
我还得以作家和记者的身份，and I still have to support my loved ones
抚养我的至亲家人，as a travel writer and a journalist,
因此很明显地，这对职业生涯，so clearly this is not ideal
for job advancement
对文化探索，or for cultural excitement
或对体验社会文化纷繁来说，
都不是一个理想的规划。or for social diversion.
但我理解，这赋予了我那些But I realized that it gives me
what I prize most,
我最珍爱的日子，which is days
与时刻。and hours.
我在那儿从未需要使用手机。I have never once had to use
a cell phone there.
我基本上几乎无须看时间，I almost never have to look at the time,
每天早上我醒来时，and every morning when I wake up,
在我眼前展开来的一天really the day stretches in front of me
是一片敞开的草地。like an open meadow.
当生活向你抛出某个重大惊喜时，And when life throws up
one of its nasty surprises,
它不只会出现一次，as it will, more than once,
当一个医生来到我房里，when a doctor comes into my room
脸上带着肃穆的表情，wearing a grave expression,
或一辆汽车在高速公路上突然改道，
漂移到我车子前方，or a car suddenly veers
in front of mine on the freeway,
我知道，在我骨子里，I know, in my bones,
正是那无所去处的时光that it's the time I've spent
going nowhere
帮助我持续保持平静，that is going to sustain me much more
那比起我在不丹和复活节岛
所度之日都要有帮助。than all the time I've spent
racing around to Bhutan or Easter Island.
我永远都会是个旅者，I'll always be a traveler --
那是我生活之所系，my livelihood depends on it --
然而旅行的美好之处在于，but one of the beauties of travel
它让你保有沉静之心，is that it allows you to bring stillness
在这莽撞与躁动的世界之中。into the motion and the commotion
of the world.
有一次，我在德国的法兰克福搭机，I once got on a plane
in Frankfurt, Germany,
一位年轻的德国女子坐到我身旁，and a young German woman
came down and sat next to me
与我展开非常友善的对谈，and engaged me
in a very friendly conversation
近 30 分钟，for about 30 minutes,
接着，她就转过身去，and then she just turned around
静静地坐在那儿 12 有个小时之久。and sat still for 12 hours.
她未曾打开屏幕，She didn't once turn on her video monitor,
她也没有拿出书本，
甚至从未睡去，she never pulled out a book,
she didn't even go to sleep,
就只是静静地坐着，she just sat still,
她那明晰和沉静已真正传授于我。and something of her clarity and calm
really imparted itself to me.
近来我注意到
有越来越多人刻意地I've noticed more and more people
taking conscious measures these days
试图在他们的生活中打开一片空间。to try to open up a space
inside their lives.
有些人参加黑洞之旅Some people go to black-hole resorts
他们会一晚花上几百美元where they'll spend hundreds
of dollars a night
只为了将自己的手机与电脑in order to hand over
their cell phone and their laptop
上缴给度假接待处。to the front desk on arrival.
有些我认识的人Some people I know,
just before they go to sleep,
并不会在睡前刷屏看信息，instead of scrolling through
their messages
或观看 YouTube 视频，or checking out YouTube,
反而就只是关灯，听音乐，just turn out the lights
and listen to some music,
他们知道，这样会有更好的睡眠，and notice that they sleep much better
在隔天一早将更神清气爽。and wake up much refreshed.
我曾经有幸地I was once fortunate enough
驾驶于洛杉矶旁的
高耸黯黑的群山之中，to drive into the high, dark mountains
behind Los Angeles,
那儿曾经住了伟大的诗人乐手 --where the great poet and singer
举世皆知的莱纳德·科恩。and international heartthrob Leonard Cohen
他曾在那儿附近作了好几年的僧人，was living and working for many years
as a full-time monk
就在博帝山禅学中心。in the Mount Baldy Zen Center.
当他在 77 岁发表了And I wasn't entirely surprised
自己的唱片专辑，when the record that he released
at the age of 77,
他故意给这个专辑取了
一个非常不性感的名称 “旧思维”，to which he gave the deliberately
unsexy title of "Old Ideas,"
然而这专辑在全球
17 个国家冲上排行榜首位，went to number one in the charts
in 17 nations in the world,
在另外 9 个国家冲上前 5 名。hit the top five in nine others.
它触动了我们内心里某种东西，Something in us, I think, is crying out
触动了躁动的人们for the sense of intimacy and depth
that we get from people like that.
一种亲密、深刻与沉静的思绪。who take the time
and trouble to sit still.
我想许多人拥有这种感觉，我当然也是，And I think many
of us have the sensation,
我们站在一个巨大的屏幕前，
距离大约两英寸，I certainly do,that we're standing about two inches away
from a huge screen,
人声鼎沸，摩肩接踵，and it's noisy and it's crowded
每一刻都在变动着，and it's changing with every second,
而那屏幕即为我们自己的人生。and that screen is our lives.
唯有向后退一步，再回头一步，And it's only by stepping back,
and then further back,
静静地屏住气，and holding still,
我们才能开始了解那画布上描绘之物，that we can begin to see
what the canvas means
并以更宽广的眼界洞察世界。and to catch the larger picture.
有些人已如此做了，他们无须来去。And a few people do that for us
by going nowhere.
因此，在这个快速转变的时代，So, in an age of acceleration,
没有什么比慢下来还要振奋人心。nothing can be more exhilarating
than going slow.
在这个失焦的时代，And in an age of distraction,
没有什么比凝神专注来得奢侈。nothing is so luxurious
as paying attention.
在这个不断变动的时代，And in an age of constant movement,
没有什么比静思来得急迫了。nothing is so urgent as sitting still.
所以，下一次当你们So you can go on your next vacation
去巴黎，夏威夷或新奥尔良度假时，to Paris or Hawaii, or New Orleans;
我保证你们会有一段美好时光，I bet you'll have a wonderful time.
但如果你们想回家，
期待满怀全新希望，But, if you want to come back home
alive and full of fresh hope,
爱这个世界，in love with the world,
我想，也许你们应该试着哪儿都别去。I think you might want
to try considering going nowhere.
谢谢各位。Thank you.
（掌声）(Applause)